Guide to the collection of Brooklyn, N.Y., Civil War relief associations records, ephemera and other material ARC.245
Brooklyn Historical Society
Collection of Brooklyn, N.Y., Civil War relief associations records, ephemera and other material
circa 1798 to 1964
1861-1866
Brooklyn Historical Society
Women's Relief Association of the City of Brooklyn
Brooklyn and Long Island Fair in Aid of the United States Sanitary Commission. (1864)
War Fund Committee (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
ARC.245
4 Linear Feet in 5 manuscript boxes and 9 boxes of various sizes
The collection was compiled over time by the Brooklyn Historical Society (formerly the Long Island Historical Society). It principally contains the records of two major Brooklyn-based Civil War relief associations, the War Fund Committee and the Women's Relief Association, including records of their various projects. A large portion of the collection documents one significant project undertaken by these organizations, the Brooklyn and Long Island Fair of 1864, also known as the Sanitary Fair. Documentation of the Fair covers both its financial aspects and the events and exhibits taking place there, and includes posters, broadsheets, printed matter, the Fair's newspaper, subscription books, admission tickets, stereographs of the New England Kitchen exhibit, and more. Some artifacts exhibited at the Fair are included in the collection, notably an album of autographed writings with contributions by Hawthorne, Longfellow, and James Fenimore Cooper, among many others. Documents concerning other relief organizations are found in the collection, including the Brooklyn Bureau of the American Freedmen's Friend Society and the Brooklyn and Long Island Christian Commission. Records of fundraising in Brooklyn for a Lincoln Monument Fund and in response to an 1866 fire in Portland, Maine, are also included. In addition, the collection holds other materials, primarily concerning the Civil War, relief efforts in cities other than Brooklyn, politics, commercial advertising, and other matters.
Other Finding Aids
The stereographs of the New England Kitchen exhibit are recorded in PastPerfect, Brooklyn Historical Society's image database, at the collection level. One representative image can be found in the database.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in the following series:
Series 1: War Fund Committee Records
Series 2: Women's Relief Association Records
Series 3: Brooklyn and Long Island Fair
Series 4: Lincoln Monument Fund
Series 5: Other Relief Organizations and Events
Series 6: Ephemera and Miscellaneous
Biographical / Historical
At the outset of the Civil War, the Red Cross did not exist, there was no draft, the nursing profession was nascent, and there existed no formal welfare relief for wounded soldiers and families of deceased soldiers. Private institutions, state and local governments, and individuals mobilized in order to meet the great demands of the war. Volunteer military regiments were formed through the efforts of state and local recruitment agencies, and relief was provided through existing channels of philanthropy, such as church groups and local welfare agencies, as well as newly-established ones created specifically to assist the war effort.
Women were especially active in these relief efforts, not only as a result of their long-standing involvement in philanthropy, but also as the moving force behind the United States Sanitary Commission (USSC), which was established early in the war in order to assist the government in supplying the needs of soldiers and providing advice and assistance to improve the medical and sanitary conditions of the army. Women's auxiliary chapters of the USSC were established throughout northern states. Cities that promoted the work of the Commission served as "depots" for the vast quantities of goods and other supplies that were collected for soldiers, and organized fund-raising events for the USSC, including concerts and fairs.
Private and public relief and recruitment activities in Brooklyn began at the beginning of the Civil War through institutions, women's organizations, and state-run channels. It quickly became apparent that the resources of the city could better be mobilized on behalf of the war effort by creating a large central committee. Accordingly, the "War Fund Committee of the City of Brooklyn and the County of Kings" was established in the summer of 1862, with headquarters at 15 Court Street in the Hamilton Building. J.S.T. Stranahan was elected chairman of the Committee and Isaac Frothingham served as its Treasurer. Stranahan, a local businessman and president of the Atlantic Docks, had been a Whig Member of Congress and a Republican presidential elector in 1860.
The Committee's literature named objectives: adding members, promoting the goals of the Sanitary Commission, performing services on behalf of the sick and wounded, aiding discharged soldiers and the families of deceased soldiers, assisting the Allotment Committee in their philanthropic work. The Committee created organizations such as the "Home Trust of the Volunteers" to aid soldiers and their families in procuring pensions and financial assistance. It also undertook to raise funds for the United States Sanitary Commission by means of appeals through churches, and raised $6,000 in May, 1863. The War Fund Committee later raised money to erect a statue in honor of assassinated President Lincoln, later erected in Grand Army Plaza at the entrance to Brooklyn's Prospect Park.
The Women's Relief Association of Brooklyn (WRA), a local auxiliary of the USSC headed by Mrs. J.S.T. Stranahan, appealed through churches to raise $50,000 for the Sanitary Commission in the fall of 1863. The WRA and the War Fund afterward sought other fundraising venues for the USSC while continuing to conduct appeals through church activities. The War Fund asked the WRA to organize a Sanitary Fair for Brooklyn, but at that time plans were already underway for the WRA's participation in New York City's Grand Metropolitan Fair on behalf of the USSC, originally scheduled to open on Feb. 22, 1864. Plans for a separate "Brooklyn and Long Island Fair" proceeded in earnest after New York City's fair was postponed to April, and opened on February 22, to run for two weeks.
The WRA and the War Fund Committee jointly sponsored the event, and members from both organizations served as the fair's executive officers. Numerous committees were formed, subscriptions solicited, and donations of goods received from all over Brooklyn and Long Island. The officers selected the Brooklyn Academy of Music, then located on Montague Street, as the principal site and two temporary structures and several private ones were afterward needed to accommodate the exhibits and other activities. The plans included publication of the first daily newspaper for any contemporary fair, Drum Beat. According to historical accounts of the fair, this newspaper averaged a daily circulation of 6,000. At the fair's closing, Treasurer James Frothingham announced that $400,000 had been raised for the Sanitary Commission, more than twice the amount of the most optimistic predictions, and well in excess of what had been raised in any city to date.
Sources for further information at BHS include: Harriet Stryker-Rodda's Brooklyn and Long Island Sanitary Fair (call E631.B76.S77) and History of the Brooklyn and Long Island Fair published by the Fair's Executive Committee (call E631.B76.H57).
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Related Materials
BHS holds various archival materials related to this collection. The best source for identifying additional materials at BHS is the Civil War subject guide, available on Emma, BHS's catablog. Some notable items are:
Committee of Reception to the Crews of the Frigates "Cumberland" and "Congress" records (call 1977.313) includes the records of a Brooklyn Civil War relief association focused on helping the survivors of a naval battle.
Brooklyn, N.Y. Civil War History collection (call 1977.006) includes the research notes Frank J. Bramhall collected for the War Fund Committee for a planned, but never written, history of Brooklyn's contributions to the war effort.
The C. B. Nichols scrapbook (call 1974.134) includes material from the Brooklyn and Long Island Fair.
The Civil War collection (call 1977.200) has a small number of printed materials associated with the War Fund Committee and the Lincoln Monument Fund.
There are various posters and other works on paper related to the Brooklyn and Long Island Fair that are not in this collection. These can be found by reference to section 3 (broadsides, prints, etc.) of the Civil War subject guide or by searching PastPerfect, a database available in the library of such objects.
Scope and Contents
The collection principally contains the records of two major Brooklyn-based Civil War relief associations, the War Fund Committee and the Women's Relief Association. A large portion of the collection concerns one significant project undertaken by these organizations, the Brooklyn and Long Island Fair of 1864, also known as the Sanitary Fair. In addition, the collection holds a miscellany of other materials, primarily concerning the Civil War or dating from the Civil War era.
Documentation of the Brooklyn and Long Island Fair covers both its financial aspects and the events and exhibits taking place there. The collection holds floor plans for the Fair site at the Academy of Music; stereographs of the New England Kitchen exhibit; a full run of Drum Beat, the Fair's newspaper, and sheet music for a song of the same name; programs; performance scripts; announcements; admission tickets; posters; placards; broadsheets; and artifacts. Several artifacts known or believed to have been exhibited at the Fair are in the collection, including a strand of George Washington's hair, a set of correspondence from the Mexican War, a scrapbook of Confederate song lyrics, and an album of autographed writings compiled by Gertrude Lefferts Vanderbilt. This album includes contributions by Hawthorne, Longfellow, and James Fenimore Cooper, among many others; a complete list of contributors is found in the container list of Series 3.
In addition to the Fair, the collection holds financial records, minute books, and print matter concerning the War Fund Committee and the Women's Relief Association's other activities. The War Fund's Home Trust of the Volunteers, Lincoln Monument Fund, and East Tennessee Fund are among the projects well-represented in the collection. Other Brooklyn and New York relief organizations from the Civil War era are included to a limited extent in the collection. These include documents from the Brooklyn Bureau of the American Freedmen's Friend Society (led by local African-Americans), the Brooklyn and Long Island Christian Commission, and the Brooklyn fund established in response to an 1866 fire in Portland, Maine. Some print matter and ephemera from other Brooklyn and New York area organizations, not necessarily engaged in relief efforts, are also in the collection. The collection also holds some material concerning sanitary fairs in other cities, especially Albany, New York City, Philadelphia, and St. Louis. Some copies of newspapers from fairs at Boston, Indianapolis, New York, and Philadelphia are in the collection.
An extensive miscellany of Civil War era materials, and some earlier, are included in the collection. These materials include wartime poems, manuscript remarks of Capt. Samuel Whiting concerning the war and his service as U.S. consul to the Bahamas, political tracts and other print matter, Confederate regiment supply requisitions, orders for the 13th and 26th regiments of the New York State National Guard (unrelated to service in the war), commercial advertising broadsheets, and a copy of Bradstreet's Commercial Reports for New England (circa 1865, partly obscured by its use as a scrapbook), among other documents.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection consists of material believed to have been collected over time and compiled by librarians at the Brooklyn Historical Society (formerly, the Long Island Historical Society). The specific sources for most of the collection are unknown. It is known that the Society, founded in 1863 less than one year before the Brooklyn and Long Island Fair, solicited donations of materials exhibited at the Fair and was no doubt active at the time in acquiring records of the Fair and its sponsoring organizations, including documents in this collection. Material of known provenance in the collection includes the following:
Mrs. Henry Sheldon, the chairwoman of the Fair's Fancy Goods Committee, donated the committee's subscription books in 1903. Brown University donated the list of subscribers to the Fair from Southampton. The book of autographed writings compiled by Gertrude Lefferts Vanderbilt was purchased at the Fair by Henry R. Pierson, and donated by Pierson to the Society in 1885. Similarly, the scrapbook of Confederate song lyrics was purchased at the Fair by J. Carson Brevoort, a frequent contributor to the Society, and the book was likely donated by him. The printing plates were donated by Jonathan B. Steel. There is some indication that the War Fund records were donated by Treasurer Frothingham and that the Women's Relief records came directly from that organization.
Donor lists; Subscription lists; Printed ephemera; Minutes; Drum beat; Poetry; Presidents |z United States |x Election |y 1864; Ledgers (account books); Receipts (financial records); Our daily fare; War |x Relief of sick and wounded; Sanitary fair bulletin; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x History |y Civil War, 1861-1865; Boatswain's whistle; Mexican War, 1846-1848 |v Correspondence; Spirit of the fair (New York, N.Y.); United States |x History |y Civil War, 1861-1865 |x Civilian relief; Correspondence; Charities |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Advertisements; Scrapbooks; Broadsides (notices); Fairs |z New York (State) |z Kings County; American newspapers; Printing plates; Stereographs; Admission tickets; Kings County (N.Y.) |v Newspapers; Manuscripts (document genre); Autographs (manuscripts); Lecture notes; War Fund Committee (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Women's Relief Association of the City of Brooklyn; Brooklyn and Long Island Fair in Aid of the United States Sanitary Commission. (1864)
- Series 1: War Fund Committee Records, 1861-1871; 4848; 0.21 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records of the War Fund Committee of the City of Brooklyn and the County of Kings, including printed items describing the origins and activities of the Committee and its members as well as several forms used by the Committee to assist soldiers and their families in applying for welfare benefits. The series also contains financial records of the Committee, including a list of recipients of the Committee's charity, transactional documents, a subscription book, receipts/expense ledger, and a bank register from the Nassau Bank of Brooklyn. A Cash Book includes records for associated relief funds: the Home Trust of the Volunteers; the East Tennessee Fund; the Committee for Relief of Sick and Wounded Soldiers; and the Calico Ball Fund for Relief of Soldiers and Families. Additional information on the activities of the Home Trust of the Volunteers is contained in the Minute Book in the series. The series includes some material, such as that concerning the Calico Ball, associated with the Brooklyn and Long Island Fair, but generally items relating to the War Fund Committee's involvement in the Fair are found in Series 3.
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged in no particular order.
  - Printed Material, circa 1862-1864; 4849 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Relief Forms, circa 1864; 4850 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Subscription Book, 1864; 4851 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Nassau Bank of Brooklyn Account Register, 1862-1871; 4852 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cash Book, 1861-1871; 4853 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Financial Transaction Records, 1864-1870; 4854 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Expense and Receipts Ledger, 1862-1864; 4855 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Home Trust of the Volunteers, Minute Book, 1861-1862; 4856 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Home Trust of the Volunteers, Subscription Book (blank), circa 1861; 4857 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series 2: Women's Relief Association Records, 1862-1866; 4858; 0.31 Linear Feet
  This series contains records of the Women's Relief Association of Brooklyn (WRA), including printed materials and reports submitted for the years 1863-1865. Detailed information regarding donations of goods and cash is found in two day books and a register of receipts. Minutes of the Association are documented in the Secretary's Book. The series includes a certificate presented by the Women's Central Association of Relief (a precursor to the WRA) to the Soldier's Aid Society in commemoration of their shared work on behalf of the sick and wounded. Artifacts included in the series are a WRA stamp and a swatch of linen from a wedding dress used for bandages (with related correspondence).
  - Printed Documents and Correspondence, 1863-1864; 4859 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Reports, 1863-1865; 4862 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Inventory of Articles for Chicago Fair, 1865; 4950 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Secretary's Book, 1862-1864; 4860 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Day Books (2 folders), 1862-1865; 4861 (Box 1, Folder 14, 15)
  - Register of Receipts, 1862-1865; 4863 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Certificate to Soldier's Aid Society, 1866; 4865 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Linen Swatch from Scotland, with Correspondence, 1864; 4868 (Box 6, Item 1)
  - Stamp, circa 1863; 4864 (Box 6, Item 2)
- Series 3: Brooklyn and Long Island Fair, circa 1799-1866, 1964; 4866; 2.33 Linear Feet
  This series contains records relating to the Brooklyn and Long Island Fair in Aid of the United States Sanitary Commission (also known as the Sanitary Fair), held in 1864. Approximately half of the series concerns financial aspects of the Fair and donations of goods to it. The other half concerns the Fair's events and exhibits.
  Financial and donation records include a cash ledger, numbered invoices, subscription books recording donations of goods (principally to the Fine Goods Committee), and correspondence of the Finance Committee. Of particular interest is Invoice 149, from George Templeton Strong, Treasurer of the USSC, acknowledging $300,000 sent to that organization as a result of the Brooklyn Fair.
  The printed forms and documents related to planning the event include a handwritten letter from Henry Ward Beecher in support of a proposal to collect autographs in an album to be auctioned at the Fair. The Committee on Art, Relics and Curiosities contains catalogs of the artwork and other items that were exhibited at the Fair. The Business Committee material contains a handwritten memo from Mrs. J.S.T. Stranahan (President of the Women's Relief Association) providing the women with "hints" regarding how best to interact with the business community and coincidentally offering posterity an interesting insight into nineteenth century behavior norms. The series also holds floor plans for the Academy of Music Fair site, stereographs of the New England Kitchen exhibit taken by photographer W.E. James, and programs, announcements, and admission tickets for various events. There are several posters, placards, and broadsides advertising Fair events or events held in the weeks leading up to the Fair; among these is the string of numbers used by the Treasurer to announce the Fair's final receipts tally of $400,000. The folder for dramatic events includes a handwritten copy of a scene from "Jem Bags in The Wandring Minstrel" and the script of "Woman in History" performed by Packer Collegiate Institute. The series includes a full run of the Fair's daily newspaper, Drum Beat, as well as a scrapbook and clippings concerning the Fair.
  The series also includes a variety of items that were exhibited and auctioned at the Fair, or believed to have been so. One of these items is an album of autographed writings by such nineteenth century literary notables as William Cullen Bryant, Nathaniel Hawthorne, Oliver Wendell Holmes, and Henry Wadsworth Longfellow. (The complete list of contributors is noted in the series container list below.) The album also includes a page from manuscripts by James Fenimore Cooper and Washington Irving. The album was compiled by Gertrude Lefferts Vanderbilt specifically to be auctioned at the Fair. Another item, less certain as to its relation to the Fair, is a set of Mexican War-era correspondence, in Spanish, between Maria Forises and her husband, Juan, at San Luis Potosi. Other artifacts include a strand of George Washington's hair, a piece of Henry Clay's coat, a scrapbook of poems/lyrics from the Confederate states, a printing plate for a leaflet from the Fair, ribbons worn by Fair officials, and sheet music for a song also called "The Drum Beat."
  A folder in the series includes material from the Long Island Historical Society (now the Brooklyn Historical Society) concerning its effort to attract donations of items acquired at the Fair. The folder also holds a historical account of the Fair written by Harriet Stryker-Rodda in 1964 to commemorate its centennial anniversary.
  The series is arranged with financial and donation records first, followed by material concerning committee activities, Fair events, artifacts, images, and ephemera. At the end of the series is a folder of material concerning the Long Island Historical Society (now Brooklyn Historical Society) and the Fair, including a 1964 booklet authored by a librarian from the Society.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Although the series includes originals of the newspaper, Drum Beat, because of its fragility, researchers will be required to use the photocopies in the collection. Researchers desiring access to the originals need to write to the Director of the Library and Archives requesting permission and explaining their need.
  - Financial Records: Vouchers 1-214 (2 folders), 1864-1865; 4869 (Box 2, Folder 1, 2)
  - Financial Records: Cash Book, 1863-1865; 4870 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Subscription Books (4 folders), 1864; 4871 (Box 2, Folder 4-7)
    General
    Most of the books relate to the Ladies' Fancy Goods Committee.
  - Subscription Book: Southampton, Long Island, 1864; 4872 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Committee on Finance and Donations, 1863-1864; 4873 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Receipt Book for Donations of Goods, 1864; 4874 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Letter from William H. Seward re: Donation of Material (copy), 1863; 4875 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Committee on Art, Relics and Curiosities, 1864; 4876 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Business Committee, 1864; 4877 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Committee of Dry Goods Merchants, 1864; 4878 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Committee of Grocers and Hardware Merchants, 1864; 4879 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Committee on Internal Arrangements, 1864; 4880 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Committee on Manufacturers and Mechanic Arts, 1864; 4881 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Committee on Post Office and Newspaper, 1864; 4882 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Committee for Queens and Suffolk Counties, 1864; 4883 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Refreshments Committee, 1864; 4884 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - New England Kitchen Committee, 1864; 4885 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Floor Plans at Academy of Music, 1864; 4905 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Posters, Placards, Broadsides, 1864; 4906 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Ribbons, 1864; 4911 (Box 13, Item 1-17)
  - Events: Dancing, 1864; 4886 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Includes Calico Ball and dance cards
  - Events: Dramatic, 1863-1864; 4887 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Includes a handwritten copy of a scene from "Jem Bags in The Wandring Minstrel" and the script of "Woman in History" performed by Packer Collegiate Institute.
  - Events: Gymnastic, 1864; 4888 (Box 3, Folder 12)